## MEL M. HERAVI, PH.D.



+1 646.303.1234

#### **ABOUT ME**

An Usability/User Experience & POC Builder, Interaction Designer and Software Developer with several years of experience supporting initiatives within the financial services industry. A participant in all aspects of the software development lifecycle (SDLC), from requirements gathering, through user centered design and other techniques, to prototyping, usability testing, and product development and an expert in W3C Web Components.

#### **TOOLS & PLATFORMS**

Windows, Unix, Mobile Devices including Tablets & Smart Phones, Microsoft Office, Adobe Suites, HTML/5, Javascript, CSS, Less, Sass, jQuery, jQuery Mobile, jQueryUI, Twitter Bootstrap, Axure, ForeUI, Phone-Gap and Various other Rapid Prototyping and development tool sets, Ionic Hybrid Mobile framework, AngularJS Single Page Applications.

### PROFESSIONAL FOCUS

- User Centered Design
- Information Architecture
- Low / High-Fidelity Prototyping
- Visual / User Experience, Interaction Design
- Extreme/Agile Development Environments
- Product Development / Management
- Legacy System Migration

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### SENIOR POC/UXD CONSULTANT

Melify Inc., New York, NY // Jul.2015 - Present

Worked for various agencies that specialize in designing, developing, and implementing effective marketing solutions. Provided business tier definition and requirements management for their software solution delivery platform.

- Served as cross-product team leader for definition and scoping of reusable business tier components
- Managed and supported component requirements development
- Provided functional definition and requirements for company's

- online collaborative tools, including Issue Manager, Document Manager, Contact Manager Server less-Chat.
- Provided onsite consulting services to company's clients
- Conducted brainstorming sessions with Product Managers,
   Designers and Developers and Created several hi-fidelity
   prototypes in an agile / extreme environments
- Managed the development team in all development phases and development in USA, India and China

#### LEAD U/X, POC DESIGNER

Barclays Bank - New York NY // Jul.2015 - Jul.2016

Designed, Prototyped and helped implement a real-time process execution system based upon Enterprise Architect Process Modeling Platform. Processes are executed in a hierarchy fashion; EA diagrams are updated in real-time to reflect the status of each process. WebSockets were employed for incremental communications between front and back end systems.

Business analysts, enterprise architects, testers, project managers and many others were involved in creating process models within EA. These proess diagrams were then consumed by the application ready for

execution. Legacy systems, Manual Inputs and Automations are integrated into a single seamless application. This project is in currently under development and refinements.

#### LEAD U/X BUILDER AND INTERACTION DESIGNER

FannieMae - Washington DC, // Jan.2015 - July.2015

Designed and prototyped FannieMae's first iPad appraisal application to be used on the field. The prototype for this application is developed using Ionic and AngularJs into a single page application. It is currently being used to evaluate and test the concept in the field. Interviewed project owner and developers and drafted a working design document and logical flow diagrams.

#### SENIOR U/X DEVELOPER AND INTERACTION DESIGNER

Fidelity Investments - Jersey City, NY // Jan.2012- Dec.2014

Created multiple High-Fidelity prototypes for usability testing and management presentations. These prototypes utilized my toolkit as well as shared component libraries embedded within the toolkit as well as new ones that were created and tested for various applications. Prototype components could be switched in real time for testing purposes and also various tools were provided for U/X engineers to update screens remotely and on demand.

Management use prototypes as means of communication with various groups internal and external while other groups use them to validate designs, workflows and other usability tests. Designed and developed a "Page Builderâ€æ to help developers construct new pages rapidly

and efficiently. Integrated Fidelity's Pattern Library Components into the code generator. Expansion and deployment of Page Builder will reduce development and deployment costs of new applications and products substantially and by orders of magnitude. Further deployment of components will allow company to make changes rapidly and efficiently without having to rewrite entire parts as is customary today.

#### INFORMATION ARCHITECT U/X MANAGER

Sapient - New York, NY // Aug 2010 - Dec.2012

Worked closely and iteratively with clients managing expectations, presenting deliverables, facilitated work sessions & workshops. Designed high fidelity wireframes in alignment with functional requirement specifications. Successful deployment of project within scope & budget recognized with praise as the first mobile website for the company and the Annuities industry.

Conducted end user needs assessment and task analysis using appropriate techniques, e.g. interviewing, ethnography, site usage data analysis, etc. Provided key solutions into technical feasibility concerns by educating development team on interaction design best practices & methodologies. Designed personas, scenarios, user flows and high

fidelity wireframes. Client list included Wellington, Bank of America, State Street, US Treasury and others.

# LEGACY SYSTEM MIGRATION SPECIALIST / USER FXPERIENCE ENGINEER

Transaction Auditing Group (TAG) - New York, NY // Sep 2007 - Aug 2010

Consulted to an independent and unbiased provider of trade performance and market quality assessment for the securities industry.

- Migrated three independent legacy systems into a single environment, using Melify Internet Toolkit as the implementation platform; and provided migration paths and solutions to facilitate the expansion into European and Asian markets
- Completed redesign of all screens, navigation and workflows
- Created interaction/workflow design for company's applications
- Tested each product with end-users and validated each use case
- Re-implemented several backend components, including database migration, reconciliations, etc.
- v Performed usability analysis, testing and enhancement of client web applications
- Integrated high end financial graphics into various screens
- Created a new European website for company's high profile customers

#### USER INTERFACE / USER EXPERIENCE ENGINEER

consulting corporation with user interface analysis, design and development of high fidelity web-based prototypes and usability testing, onsite and remote. Mentored group members in component-based UI design as applied to Internet. Managed three high-net worth insurance-related applications.

- Managed and processed development requests with stakeholders
- Performed high fidelity prototyping of portals within customer website
- Performed usability analysis, testing and enhancement of client web applications v Created interaction/workflow design for customers' applications

#### SYSTEM ARCHITECT / SOFTWARE DESIGN ENGINEER

Hewlett Packard (HP) - Mahwah, NJ // Apr 2004 - Nov 2006

Designed and developed a comprehensive Remote Software Testing Tool for a technology solutions provider's line of products utilizing participatory design and usability analysis. This application is a multiplatform, test bed currently running on HP/UX, UNIX, Windows and Mac OSX platforms. The test bed has distributed multi-tiered architecture, and a web based UI.

- Managed product requirements
- Conducted user research for internal applications, using contextual inquiry techniques
- Created scenarios, information architecture and task flows for test bed system of applications v Produced low/high fidelity prototypes and visual designs for its web components
- Conducted brainstorming sessions with product managers, designers, developers and end users
- Guided development team with product and interaction requirements v Conducted usability walkthroughs and formative usability tests

#### LEAD USER EXPERIENCE DESIGNER

Lockheed Martin - Baltimore, MD // Jan 2003 - Apr 2004

Worked for global security company that is principally engaged in the research, design, development, manufacture, integration and sustainment of advanced technology systems, products and services. Designed and developed a comprehensive Test Environment and provided usability engineering and UCD support for a federal government agency. Designed and developed a unique Internet based test bed and survey application. Prototyped the Adult Disability web application and remotely tested the product with over 100 end users and advocates in various states.

- Participated in various UCD sessions
- Designed user interaction for Adult with Disability website
- Conceptualized, prototyped and created visual designs
- Created test scripts and conducted, along with agency team,

usability tests with users v conducted remote testing same application with over 100 remote users

#### ANALYST / LEAD PRODUCT MANAGER

RedOlive Inc, New York, NY// Dec 2000 - Jan 2003

Worked for various agencies that specialize in designing, developing, and implementing effective marketing solutions. Provided business tier definition and requirements management for their software solution delivery platform.

- Served as cross-product team leader for definition and scoping of reusable business tier components
- Managed and supported component requirements development
- ovided functional definition and requirements for company's online collaborative tools,including Issue Manager, Document Manager, Contact Manager Server less-Chat § Provided onsite consulting services to company's clients
- Conducted brainstorming sessions with Product Managers,
   Designers and Developers v Created several hi-fidelity prototypes in an agile / extreme environments
- Conducted usability tests with internal and external users
- Managed the development team in all development phases and development

#### LEAD PRODUCT ARCHITECT / DEVELOPER

Gill & Company LLC - San Francisco, CA // Jan 1999 - Dec 2000

Designed system architecture and functional/user requirements for a full-service financial advisory firm's in-house online equity trading system. Utilized participatory/User Centered design process in development of customer, functional, and user requirements specifications. This online system covered Portfolio Management, Order/Risk Management, Customer Workflow management, and direct real-time Trading with NYSE including Market making activities. Helped create and develop the application from the ground up in less than nine months (half the estimated time) with the aid of three other developers.

- Educated management on benefits of prototyping, usability testing, participatory iterative design processes as well as UXD
- signed the initial application from brainstorming with Management Traders and back office personnel
- Created an initial prototype that was tested and accepted by all participants in less than a month
- Organized and managed the development team from software selection to actual implementation

#### ANALYST / POC DESIGN ENGINEER

New York Stock Exchange (NYSE) - New York, NY // Jun 1996 - Jan 1999 Helped NYSE'S Human Factors engineering group by providing

customer/user requirements analysis, UI design and prototyping, and usability testing. Used participatory design and object-oriented design and analysis and structured processes to support rapid, iterative environment. Designed and developed a component-based architecture as well as a RAD software environment, including several re-usable libraries. Created an effective evolutionary prototyping process for NYSE software development.

- Created a Rapid Prototyping Environment for NYSE
- Conducted UCD sessions with stakeholders and documented results
- Shared documents with all participants and consolidated ideas through iterations
- Created interaction diagrams, walk-through and scenarios
- Designed two pixel-for-pixel prototypes for Display-Book and Broker Booth Support System v Tested prototypes with traders and management and generated several reports
- Shared and discussed various documents with SIAC, the development wing of NYSE

#### **EDUCATION**

- Manchester, England Ph.D. (Aerospace Engineering)
- Manchester, England M.Sc. (Computational Fluid Dynamics)
- Manchester, England B.Sc. (Mechanical Engineering)

MEL M. HERAVI, PH.D.